Guide to the Consumer Reports. Morris Kaplan papers, 1948-1972 RL.11857
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Morris Kaplan papers
1948-1972
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11857
6.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Morris Kaplan was a chemist who served as Technical Director of Consumers Union from 1946 until his death in 1971. The Morris Kaplan papers include correspondence, articles, laboratory and research reports, speeches and other printed materials. Topics include automotive safety, cigarettes, food safety, government regulations, motor oil, quality control, safety standards, testing methods and textile labeling. Organizations represented in the collection include American Standards Association; International Organization of Consumers' Unions; National Bureau of Standards, and USA Standards Institute. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General and Administrative Files; Slide Shows and Lectures
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Morris Kaplan was a chemist who served as Technical Director of Consumers Union from 1946 until his death in 1971. Kaplan was born in 1911 in New York. He attended City College of New York (BS Chemistry, 1932) and George Washington University (MS Organic Chemistry, 1939). He served as Assistant Director of hte Washington Office of the U.S. Customs Lab (1936-1942); Chemist at the U.S. Customs Laboratory (1942-1944); and Materials Engineer at the Philadelphia Navy Yard (1944-1947). Kaplan joined Consumers Union as Technical Director in 1946; in addition he served as Chairman of the International Organization of Consumers' Unions' Research Committee from its inception in 1960 until 1971. He died in 1971 and was succeeded as Technical Director by Monte Florman.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Morris Kaplan papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports Archives records
Consumer Reports. Irving Michelson papers
Consumer Reports. Monte Florman papers
Collection Overview
The Morris Kaplan papers include correspondence, articles, laboratory and research reports and other printed materials. Topics include automotive safety, cigarettes, food safety, government regulations, motor oil, quality control, safety standards, testing methods and textile labeling. Organizations represented in the collection include American Standards Association; International Organization of Consumers' Unions; National Bureau of Standards, and USA Standards Institute.
Consumer education; Consumer advocacy; consumer protection; Product safety; Kaplan, Morris; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; International Organization of Consumers' Unions
- General and Administrative Files, 1948-1972; 1
  - Office Files, 1948-1972; 1
    - Air Conditioning, Heating and Refrigeration News interview, 1963 (Box 1)
    - American Standards Association, 1960-1965 (Box 1)
    - American Standards Association--Consumer Goods Standards Board minutes, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - American Standards Association--Consumer Goods Standards Board committee and conference minutes, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - American Standards Association--Correspondence, 1958-1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Anechoic chamber, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Articles, testimonies, 1961-1971 (Box 1)
    - Association of Home Appliance Manufacturers, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Audio Lab book and equipment loans, 1957-1962 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Cigarettes, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
    - Codex Committee on Food Hygiene, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - Consumers Union and government agencies, 1962-1967 (Box 2)
    - Consumers Union and government agencies--Government Services Administration (GSA), Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), 1971 (Box 2)
    - Consumers Union and government agencies--Health, Education and Welfare (HEW) toy safety, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Consumers Union and government agencies--National Academy of Engineers, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Consumers Union policy, 1950-1971 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1970; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    - Criteria for selecting projects for Consumers Union lab testing, approximately 1955-1956 (Box 3)
    - Death related--Obituaries, memorial letters, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Fred Boggis (Brady Memorial Fellow), 1965-1968 (Box 3)
    - International Organization of Consumer Unions (IOCU), 1962-1966; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Laboratory memos and progress reports, folder 7, 1962-1967; 2 folders (Box 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Note: Folders 1-5 weeded 3/1965; Folder 6 weeded 2/1970
    - Lowell Dodge (Ralph Nader Auto Safety Fellow), 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Lyons, Ashton, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Michelson, Irving, 1958-1964 (Box 4)
    - Motor oil change intervals, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Notes and miscellaneous, 1949-1971 (Box 4)
    - Operations Committee, 1959-1965; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Planning Committee, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Personal papers, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
    - Personnel--Staff memos, policy, 1956-1964; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - President's Committee on Consumer Interests--Report on textiles and clothing, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Publications Committee, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Quality control, 1954-1957 (Box 5)
    - Safety standards, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Seminar on design, Syracuse University, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Smith, Wray, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Speech invitations, correspondence, 1962-1971; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Speeches, 1948-1962; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Speeches, 1963-1971; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Test methods correspondence, 1963-1970; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Test Sample Division progress reports, 1964-1966 (Box 6)
    - Texas Engineering Experiment Station, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Textile labeling, 1961; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - U.S. Department of Commerce Ad Hoc Committee on Standardization, 1963 (Box 7)
    - USA Standards Institute--Committee on Consumer Standards, 1969-1970; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - USA Standards Institute--Committee on Consumer Standards, 1971-1972; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Auto Test Division, 1964-1972; 2
    - Accounting, 1967-1971 (Box 8)
    - Automotive safety, 1969-1971; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - General, 1968-1971 (Box 8)
    - Legal files, 1964-1972 (Box 8)
    - Legal files, 1964-1972 (Box 10)
    - Personnel--Staff memos, policy, 1964-1969 (Box 8)
  - National Bureau of Standards, 1964-1972; 3
    - CS209-71 Committee--Vinyl Chloride plastic hose, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - Evaluation Panel, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Joseph Kanagy--NBS Research Fellow, 1968 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1971 (Box 9)
    - NBS Research Fellows, 1964-1967 (Box 9)
- Slide Shows and Lectures, 1963-1970; 2
  - Appliance Laboratory notes, approximately 1965 (Box 11)
  - Audio equipment testing notes, approximately 1966 (Box 11)
  - Lecture notes and note cards, 1963-1970 (Box 11)
  - Slides, approximately 1965 (Box 12)
    Closed for preservation.